<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
    xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
    <channel>
        <title>Anh Duy's blog</title>
        <link>https://anhduy.io</link>
        <description><![CDATA[]]></description>
        <atom:link href="https://anhduy.io/rss.xml" rel="self"
                   type="application/rss+xml" />
        <lastBuildDate>Sun, 21 Jan 2018 00:00:00 UT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
    <title>Vim package management</title>
    <link>https://anhduy.io/posts/2018-01-18-vim-package.management.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<article>
    <section class="header">
        
    </section>
    <section>
        <p>Wellcome back, it’s been a week since my first post. This week i want to write about new vim 8 pacakge management.</p>
<p>Before vim 8, to manage plugins, normally you need to install a third-party plugin management such as Pathogen, vim-plug… but starting from vim 8, you can use built-in vim package management to do that.</p>
<p>First, let’s upgrade vim to version 8. You can install it using your OS package management (pacman, brew, …), just make sure it is version 8.</p>
<p><em>I should probably introduce more about vim, but there are some plugins i can’t live without so I need to setup package management first. I promise i will introduce how to use vim later.</em></p>
<p>Here is how vim 8 package management work:</p>
<pre><code>.vim
└── pack
    └── anhduy
        ├── opt
        └── start</code></pre>
<ul>
<li><code>anhduy</code>: You can name this directory whatever you want, vim doesn’t care about this folder name.</li>
<li><code>start</code>: Always loaded plugins directory: put the plugin you want vim to load here.</li>
<li><code>opt</code>: Optional plugins directory: vim will not load plugins inside this folder unless you ask it to by running <code>:packadd</code>.</li>
</ul>
<p>Now, if you want to install <a href="https://github.com/ctrlpvim/ctrlp.vim">ctrlp</a>, just clone it into <code>start</code> and vim will autoload it.</p>
<p>Try another one, clone <a href="https://github.com/majutsushi/tagbar">Tagbar</a> into <code>opt</code>, then confirm that you can’t run <code>:Tagbar</code> until you run <code>:packadd tagbar</code> first.</p>
<p>That’s all of it, now you can use plugins with vim itself without any other tools.</p>
<p>Questions from (imagination) readers:</p>
<pre><code>Q: What do you mean by &quot;clone it into start&quot;?
A: That&#39;s a git specific term, basically it mean you copy the whole folder and put it inside start directory.</code></pre>
<pre><code>Q: Can vim package management allow me to define plugins in vimrc or have command to download plugins?
A: No, it only know how to load your plugins.</code></pre>
<pre><code>Q: So now my vimrc isn&#39;t the source of truth, which defined all my vim config anymore?
A: ...</code></pre>
<pre><code>Q: If i use this, how can i copy by vimrc to a server and use it, before that i have vim-plug download everything for me
A: ... ...</code></pre>
<pre><code>An early converted reader: I removed vim-plug and use vim 8 pacakge management now, it works fine, but how can i update my plugins?
A: ... ... ...</code></pre>
<pre><code>Another early converted: This thing is useless, it can&#39;t update my plugins likes vim-plug. How can i update my plugin :rage: ?
A: :dont-know: :who-care:</code></pre>
<pre><code>Others: Wait, wait, I don&#39;t understand, what should i do now, please answer above questions :crying:
A: :dun-care: :dun-care: :running-away:</code></pre>
<p>Thanks for reading, see you again next time on how to setup and use vim as main editor.</p>
    </section>
    <section class="footer">
        January 18, 2018
    </section>
    <section class="license">
	    <a rel="license" href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/"><img alt="Creative Commons License" style="border-width:0" src="https://i.creativecommons.org/l/by-nc-nd/4.0/80x15.png" /></a><br />This work is licensed under a <a rel="license" href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License</a>.
    </section>
</article>
]]></description>
    <pubDate>Thu, 18 Jan 2018 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>https://anhduy.io/posts/2018-01-18-vim-package.management.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>Anh Duy</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>New blog</title>
    <link>https://anhduy.io/posts/2018-01-06-new-blog.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<article>
    <section class="header">
        
    </section>
    <section>
        <p>It’s 2018, I think it’s time for me to start writing blog posts. A lot of people told me writing will improve my thinking, my understanding on the topic i write. Also, by writing, I hope I can share things I am passionate about to larger audience.</p>
<p>I will mainly write posts about these topics:</p>
<ul>
<li>Strong typed language: after learning a bit of Haskell and Idris, I am very interested in how these languages can help us write better software.</li>
<li>Unix-like system and cli tools: I spend most of my time in tmux and vim, I believe terminal apps can help you boost your productivity a lot compared to GUI app. Also I would like to understand more about Unix-like system. I am using Arch linux but also keep an eye on NixOS.</li>
<li>Devops tools: vm, container, scheduler … One day I will control one thousand servers by myself.</li>
<li>Others: can be random topics that catches my attention, such as c, compiler, build x from scratch or how special Nier: Automata is and you should play it.</li>
</ul>
<p>That’s it for the first post to test out my setup, see you next week.</p>
<p><em>P/S: Did you know you can read this blog without JavaScript? And yes, it’s responsive.</em></p>
    </section>
    <section class="footer">
        January  6, 2018
    </section>
    <section class="license">
	    <a rel="license" href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/"><img alt="Creative Commons License" style="border-width:0" src="https://i.creativecommons.org/l/by-nc-nd/4.0/80x15.png" /></a><br />This work is licensed under a <a rel="license" href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License</a>.
    </section>
</article>
]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sat, 06 Jan 2018 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>https://anhduy.io/posts/2018-01-06-new-blog.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>Anh Duy</dc:creator>
</item>

    </channel>
</rss>
